<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of the vanquishing of the towne of Olinda cituated in the Capitania of Phernambuco. Through the renowned and valiant sea-man Henry C. Longk, generall by sea and land, and Diderick van Wardenburgh, coronell ouer the militarie by land, for the licensed West-India companie, vnder the high and mightie lords the States of the United Provinces. Hereto is also annexed a letter of the coronell Wardenburgh to the States Generall. Also a map of the cituation of the towne and forts.</title>
            <author>Loncq, Hendrik Cornelis. b. 1568.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06205</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104908</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840638</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840638</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5162</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5162)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 893:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of the vanquishing of the towne of Olinda cituated in the Capitania of Phernambuco. Through the renowned and valiant sea-man Henry C. Longk, generall by sea and land, and Diderick van Wardenburgh, coronell ouer the militarie by land, for the licensed West-India companie, vnder the high and mightie lords the States of the United Provinces. Hereto is also annexed a letter of the coronell Wardenburgh to the States Generall. Also a map of the cituation of the towne and forts.</title>
                  <author>Loncq, Hendrik Cornelis. b. 1568.</author>
                  <author>Waerdenburgh, Dirk van. Copie vande missive, gheschreven byden Generael Weerdenburch. English. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p. : maps  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ian Fredericksz Stam in de Hope,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Amstelredam [sic] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno M.DC.XXX. [1630]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of the original.</note>
                  <note>Includes two maps, bound at end of text.</note>
                  <note>Slight print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Olinda (Brazil) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:5162:1"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:5162:1"/>
            <head>DESCRIPTION Of the takeing of PHERNAMBOVCQVE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Valiant and renowned Generall H.C. LONCK, ſailed out of Goeree with 8. Ships the 27 Iune 1629 and came vnder Tenerifa in the Canaries, where hee was in fight with the Armade of Don FREDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RICO the 23. and 24. Auguſt. and the 4. September hee ariued in S. Vincent, where hee refreſhed, and the 29. Novem. came by him the Coronel D. van WARDENBURGE, as alſo did the Commander DIRRICK SYMONSZ come thither the 29. of the ſame moneth, who ſayled out of Texel with the ſaid Coronel the 20. October: The Fleet beeing then ſtrong 50. Ships &amp; Pinaſſes, 2. Pryſes and 13. great Shalloups, where was muſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red 7280. Men iong and olde, towit 3780 Mariners and 3500 Souldiers. With which Forces according to his order hee ſett his courſe towards the Coaſt of Pernambuco, and got land in ſight the 2. February vpon 7. degrees 4. Minutes, and the 13. of February aboute C.S. Auguſtijn: Where was reſolued that the Coronell with 16. Ships and Pinaſſes, and 2400. Souldiers and 600. Mariners ſhould land 2. mile northwards of Pernam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buco in Rio Doce: and the Generall with the reſt of the Fleete and 2. ſtrong Companies of Souldiers ſhould ſaile to the Recif. Which reſolution beeing taken, the 13. and 14. they prepared themſelves and all things readie, and the 15. by breake of the daye, with milde weather and a ſtill ſea, they began there Enterpriſe, towit the Generall ſetting towards the Recif vnto the Barra of Pernambuco, and the Coronell Wardenborge with his 16. ſaile, wherein was 2400. Souldiers and 600. Mariners, whoe beeing landed preſentlie ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the appointed place.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:5162:2"/>
            <p>The Generall came to the Barra aforeſaid aboute noone, and ſailed with ſom ſhips cloſe vnder the Fort, which lies vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Recif, vpon which hee plaied with his Ordinance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the euening, and likewiſe vpon the land Forts. The Forts alſo plaied luſtilie vpon the Ships and with advantage, for the Ships coulde not ſhoote leuel by reaſon of the wauering of the ſea, and when they lighted vpon the Walls, it made one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie whit ſpots without doeing anie damage to the Forts one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie a little at the verie top of the Walles.</p>
            <p>6. Ships and 11. Pinaſſes remained readie with ſmale ſaile to run in, when warning ſhould bee giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at high water, which was expected aboute 3. of the clock. But the Governour of Pernambuco it ſeemes was long afore advertiſed of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of this Fleete, and therevpon had ſtopped the mouth of the River of the Recif (namelie the Poco and Barette) with ſoncked Ships, and fenced the whole Vilage Povo vpon the land Recif with a little wall or breaſtworck, ſo that the Ships and Pinaſſes at that time could effect nothing, and the other Ships which laye-cloſe vnder the Wall were conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to drawe back toward the euening.</p>
            <p>In the meane while the Coronel Wardenborgh was buſie with landing his Forces with Shalloups and Boates at the place appointed, and marched formoſt himſelfe with the vantguarde, in ſight of his Enimies, who ſhewed themſelues ſtrong both a foote and horſeback along the ſtrand, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the reſt of the Forces followed out of the Ships, with 2 pieces of Ordinance which ſhott 3. pound iron, but the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning drawing on, they were conſtrained to lodge one the ſtrand vnder the ſkie that night.</p>
            <p>In the night time haueing made all preparation, the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning drawing one hee martched forwards corragiouſlie with all his Forces, parted in 3. Regiments and a partie of Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks, the vantguard vnder which the Coronell was himſelfe, was commaunded by Lieutennant Eltſz: the Battaillion by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5162:2"/>Lieutennant Steyncalenfels, and the rierguard by the Major Houx, haueing on there one ſide a thik groue, out of which they feared much to bee annoyed.</p>
            <p>By Rio Doce which is a running River (where they were conſtrained to march through to the middel) they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred of the Portingals, who laie there entrenched ſome 1800. ſtrong, the ſkirmidge was hot and ours put back twice, and manie ſlaine and hurt one both ſides, but moſt one the Enimies ſide, and ſo at laſt they were put to flight.</p>
            <p>From thence the Coronell marched to the Towne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſting, takeing by the waye ſome blaks, but learning noe intelligence from them, coming to the Towne they aſſaulted the Ieſuites Cloſter, the gates whereof were bolwerkt toe within ſide, which beeing beaten open and all ſlaine that reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, the Enimies were forced to forſake the Cloſter, leauing behinde manie dead and maimed.</p>
            <p>The Enimies forces in the Trenches and Forts one the Strand along the Sea, heareing ſuch newes, and perceiueing Major Houx coming againſt them with the reareguard, tooke the flight alſo after a little ſkirmidging, and playing of the Ordinance, leaueing behinde them ſome few dead and hurt.</p>
            <p>In the meane time that the Coronell approached the Towne one the North ſide, the Generall had landed 2. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies with good convenience one the South ſide, and ſent them to aſſiſt the Coronell, and ſo the Towne was aſſaulted one both ſides, in ſuch manner that aboute 4. of the clock in the afternoone it was ouercome with loſſe of aboute 50. or 60. Souldiours.</p>
            <p>After the winning of the Towne there was found within but aboute 100. Chiſts with Sugar, ſome Wines, little Meal and other ſmall matters of little vallew, becauſe the Cittizens and Inhabitants were fled with moſt part of there goods, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Governour MATTHIAS d'ALBUQUERQUE had forbidden it vpon paine of death, that noe bodie ſhould
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5162:3"/>flie, or carrie ought out of the Towne, becauſe the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants might help to keepe the Towne the better.</p>
            <p>In the night the Generall cauſed the hauen mouthes to be founded, and the Forts to bee viewed, which the Enimie did holde ſtronglie beſet, ſo that there was ſmale hope to doe anie good againſt them by water.</p>
            <p>The 17. February the Governour cauſed all the Packhouſes to bee ſet on fire, wherein was aboue 15000. Chiſts of Sugar, becauſe the Inhabitants were fled as a priſoner reported, which fire coulde not bee hindered by ours.</p>
            <p>The 20. after the Towne was well beſet and good order ſet in all things, there was reſolued by the Counſell to make an Enterprinſe vpon the Fort, which layes vpon the land Recif; where to the Coronel commaunded the Lieutennant Steyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calenfelts with 400. or 500. Men, whoe quited himſelfe well in that Action, and ſtormed twoo houres in the night vpon the Fort, but beeing the ſkaling Ladders, which were raiſed were found a faddem to ſhort, and that the gates coulde not bee opened, becauſe thoſe of the ſmale Fort that lies vpon the Sea Recif, did much annoye ours with there Cannons, wee reſolued to retraite to ſpare our Men, leaueing behinde vs aboute 20. dead and 40. or 50. hurt.</p>
            <p>The 21. the Barrette beeing viſited with Shalloups, whoe ſet fire on the Ship that the Enimies had ſunck in the mouth with ſtones to ſtop the paſſage, which Ship beeing fired, they found good convenience to come within the Recif with Shalloups, but ſeeing the Village vpon the Recif, where the Packhouſes were fired, was ſo fenced with Walles, Breſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woorks and Paliſades, it was thought verie dangerous to land there to attempt anie thing againſt the Village.</p>
            <p>And the 22. beeing buſie to ſtrengthen the Towne with more Workes, and alſo the Ieſuites Cloſter, and likewiſe in makeing a Bridge at the Foote of the Towne, which ſhoulde come out ouer the Bar like a head a little Seawards to land;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5162:3"/>and carrie aboord anie thing drie in time of neede.</p>
            <p>The 23. was reſolued with approbation of all the Officers to drawe neare the Fort (that lies vpon the land Recif) with Approaches, whereto all preparation of Foſſiues and Sconce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſkets were made, moſt of the Mariners beeing imployed aboute cutting Rijſwork and makeing Sconce-baſkets, and others finiſheing of the ſaid Bridge.</p>
            <p>And the 25. haueing finiſhed diuers Breſtworks in manie ſtreets of the Towne, againſt anie ſuddaine Enterpriſe of the Enimie, the Approaches towards the greate Fort were began the 29. Februarie by the Lieutennant Eltſz, with 500. Men, who caſt vp a Trench the ſame night againſt the Fort, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Village (that lies vpon the Recif) and the Towne: and the next daye had Almoſt finiſhed a Batterie, when the Major Houx came to relieue him, whereto the Coronell alſo repaired and remained there vntill the next daye, vntill the Batterie was finiſhed, and 3. halfe Cartouwes planted, which played the whole daye.</p>
            <p>And afterwards beeing the 2. March, haueing played all the morning with the Ordinance, thoſe of the Fort rolled vp there Auncient, and put out a white ſheete and ſo ſought to parle, ſending out a Captaine, who agreed with the Coronell to deliuer ouer the Fort vpon Conditions as hereafter follow in the Articles.</p>
            <p>This beeing don the Coronell reſolued to demand vp the Fort which lies vpon the Sea Recif, and therevpon hee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſed his intent to the Generall and the reſt of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, who all ratified the ſame, and ſo it was put in practiſe, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out a Tambour and an Interpreter, who they of the Fort preſentlie gaue audience, and ſent out there Lieuten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant (taking another in hoſtage in his place) who agreed with the Coronell in like manner as thoſe of the other Fort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id, and therevpon marched out.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:5162:4"/>
            <p>The next daye beeing the 3. of March the Generall gaue commaundement vnto the Lieutennant Steyncalenfelts, to make en Enterpriſe vpon the Iland, called Antonie Vaz, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated ouer againſt the Village vpon the Recif, where beeing ſet ouer hee found noe reſiſtance, the Inhabitants beeing fled haueing heard the winning of the Caſtles, ſo hee lodged a Troup of Souldiers in the Cloſter, which ſtands vpon the Iland, where with the Towne and Fortreſſes of Pernambuco are all in hands of the Officers of licenſed Weſt-India Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, vnder protection of the States Generall and the Prince of Orenge, which God long continu to his glorie.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye that the mouth of the Recif was ſounded, ſom Ships, Pinnaſſes and all the Shalloups run into the Recif, which is a verie convenient place, not onelie to laye ſhips in, but alſo te make them cleane and keele them, and the Pinnas that ſhould depart with the good newes was made cleane there in the Recif, and loaden with ſom Sugars. The Lord Generall being lodged in the Povo vpon the Recif: The Coronell in the Ieſuits Cloſter; and the Lieutennant Coronel vpon the Iland of Antonie Vaz.</p>
            <div type="armistice">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:5162:4"/>
               <head>Articles agreed betwixt the Lord Generall H. C. LONCQ, and Coronell WARDENBURGH on the one pertie, and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ANTONIO DE LIMA, Captaine of the ſtrong Fort S. George, for his Maieſtie of Spaine, on the other pertie.</head>
               <p>FIrſt that Captaine ANTONIO DE LIMA doth binde him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to deliuer ouer to the Lord Generall and Coronel WARDENBURGH the ſtrong Fort S. George, with all the Ordinance and Amonition whatſoeuer now in the ſaid Fort.</p>
               <p>Item that the ſaid Captaine Antonio de Lima after delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ouer of the faid Fort, ſhall depart the ſame with all his Souldiers, with there ordinarie Weapons, without Auncient or burning Matches, and ſo bee ſet ouer with Barques vpon the faſt Land, to march whither they pleaſe.</p>
               <p>And for ſecuritie of the ſaide Barques the ſaid Captaine de Lima ſhall remaine in hoſtage till the Barques returne, and then vpon his faithfull oath and ſaluation doth promiſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne the Barque (that ſhall tranſport his perſon) vndamni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
               <p>And further the ſaid Captaine de Lima doth promiſe for him and his Souldiers, not to ſerue againſt the States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or the Prince of Orenge in 6. Monethes.</p>
               <p>All theſe Articles are approoued by both perties in the Campe before the ſtrong Fort S. George the 2. March 1630. And was ſubſcribed H. C. LONCK, Generall. T. van WAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DENBURGH Coronell. And ANT. DE LIMA, Captaine of the ſtrong Fort S. George.</p>
               <p>Theſe Articles are alſo agreed vpon betwixt the ſaide Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and Coronell, and Manuel Pacheco el Guyar, Captaine Major, and Pedro Barboſa Lieutenant of the Fort vpon Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="register">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:5162:5"/>
               <head>Regiſter of the Ammonition found in <hi>PHERNAMBVCO.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Vpon the 2. Forts vpon the Strand by North and South-ſide of the Towne, found in each 4. iron Pieces, ſhooteing 4. <abbr>lb</abbr> Iron.
<list>
                           <item>8. Peeces.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item> 

<list>
                           <item>Vpon both the Forts or Caſtles 600 <abbr>lb</abbr> Powder.</item>
                           <item>In the Ieſuites Cloſter 30 Barrells Powder, each eſteemed 100 <abbr>lb</abbr> makes 3000 <abbr>lb</abbr>
                           </item>
                           <item>Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Tolehouſe 5 Barrels each eſteemed 200 <abbr>lb</abbr> is 1000 <abbr>lb.</abbr>
                              <list>
                                 <item ana="#role_TOTAL">Somma 4600 <abbr>lb</abbr> Powder.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Aboute 2000 <abbr>lb</abbr> Match.</item>
                     <item>More aboute 200 <abbr>lb.</abbr>
                     </item>
                     <item>A percell of iron Bullets of 20 in the <abbr>lb.</abbr>
                     </item>
                     <item>Som Rods of Lead.</item>
                     <item>Som Boxes with Muſket Bullets of 12 in the <abbr>lb.</abbr>
                     </item>
                     <item>A greate quantitie Spaniſh Iron in Staves.</item>
                     <item>2. Hoghheads Saltpeeter.</item>
                     <item>A percell Shouels.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Artillerie vpon the Fort S. George, cituated by the Packhouſes.</head>
                     <item>24 Iron Peeces ſhooteing 10 a 5 <abbr>lb</abbr> iron.</item>
                     <item>4000 <abbr>lb</abbr> Powder.</item>
                     <item>A percell Iron Bulletts.</item>
                     <item>30 <abbr>lb</abbr> greate Muſket Bullets of 10 in the <abbr>lb.</abbr>
                     </item>
                     <item>40 <abbr>lb</abbr> Match.</item>
                     <item>A percell Hand-granades.</item>
                     <item>A percell Fire-potts.</item>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:5162:5"/>
                     <item>1 Braſſe peece ſhooting 8 <abbr>lb.</abbr>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 Pipes Spaniſh Wijn.</item>
                     <item>1 Chiſt Sugar.</item>
                     <item>A percell greate Pottyſes with Water.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>In the Caſtel vpon the Sea Recif is found as followeth.</head>
                     <item>15 Braſſe Ordinance wherevpon ſtands the Armes of Phillip the II. and III. Kings of Spaine, and ſome the Armes of Portugall, ſhooting ſome 20.18. and 10 <abbr>lb</abbr> Iron.</item>
                     <item>1 Braſſe Piece a ſnake of 10 <abbr>lb</abbr> Iron, ſpoiled.</item>
                     <item>14 Barrels of Powder of 120 <abbr>lb.</abbr>
                     </item>
                     <item>A percell of Iron Cannon Bullets.</item>
                     <item>A greate partie Cardoeſes to the Peeces.</item>
                     <item>A percell of greate and ſmale Pottyſes filled with water, Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Wyne and Viniger.</item>
                     <item>7 Sacks Meale, 4 Chiſts Farinie.</item>
                     <item>Some ſalted Fiſh.</item>
                     <item>1 Tub with ſalted Fleſh.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:5162:6"/>
            <head>HIGH AND MIGHTIE LORDS.</head>
            <p>SEEING that with Gods aſſiſtance I haue victoriouſly conquered this Towne of FARNABUCCO, I could not omitt according to my duty, participate vnto you, what is paſſed therein as farr as preſent tyme will permitt.</p>
            <p>In the Bay of S. Vincent hauing found the Generall LONCK with his accompanyed Shipps, wee weare in all (after ſome weekes being gathered together 53. ſayles of Shipps, with healthy and ſickly Souldiers, ſayled from thence the 26. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb. 1629. towards the coaſts of Braſill, where wee came the 12. February, in the clymake of 8. degrees, where there came vnto vs ſome Shipps and Pynnaces, which had loſt vs and weare ſent out before vs, ſo that afterwards wee weare 56. ſayle; Whereafter ſerious deliberation wee reſolued to fall vpon the Ennemy in twoo places, to witte I with 2400. Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and 300. Saylers, with 300. Saylers more to the traine being deuided in 16. Shipps, were reſolued to land about 2. Myles towards the North of Fernambucco: And the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall LONCK hauing by him two other ſtrong Companyes in the other Shipps towards the Recyf, hauing reſolued the 15. February to effect our enterpriſe. The Generall going to the Recyf, but by reaſon thoſe of the Caſtell had heard of our comming, they had ſunck certayne ſhipps in the mouth of the Hauen, ſo that the Generalls deſſeyn toock noe effect allbeitt hee did his beſt indeauours with ſhott of Cannon; in the meane tyme in the afternoone I went towards the ſhoare in certayne Sloopes, where there did apeare many Souldiers, both foote and horſe; and being landed in their ſight, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the reſt of our Souldiers followed out of the other Shipps with 2. Peeces that ſhott 3. <abbr>lb</abbr> Iron, and becauſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gann to growe euening, wee weare forced to lodge vpon the ſtrand: Next morning very early I did ſend the Boats towards the Shipps, and ſeparated my Troupes in three Regiments.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5162:6"/>The Auantguarde where I was in perſon, aſwell in marching as in landing, was commaunded by Leftennant Eltſz: The Battell by Leftennant Steyncallenfells: The Rierguarde by Major Houcks, marching on the ſtrand towards the Towne, comming by Rio Dolce was a ſmale Riuer, which wee weare forced to wade to the middle in water, where wee had the firſt aſſault, wheare the Ennemy as I am aduiſed weare about 1800 Men, both foote and horſe, did reſiſt vs but after a hard Skermiſh, and many being dead and hurt on both ſides, but leaſt of our ſide they weare putt to flight. Notwithſtanding they had a running Riuer for their aduantage. Comming ſomwhat further, ſtood another Troupe vpon the ſtrand, but after little reſiſtance did alſo retired in the Woods, ſhowing themſelues the third tyme, durſt not ſtay for vs; ſo that with all diligence ſeing them ſo frighted, I marched towards the Towne, drawing neare therevnto with the Auantguarde and Battaille, did amount vnto the Ieſuitts Cloyſter, where the Backgates weare bollwarckt, and wee in clyming, ſawe them in the Cloyſter arme themſelues, but after ſome reſiſtance, and hauing ſeene our courage, they fleyed, leauing behind them many dead and wounded, and of our Men weare alſo ſome ſlayne. In the meane tyme the Trenches and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes haueing notice heereof, and ſeing the Rearguarde, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo haſtily vpon them, after many ſhott with Canon, and ſome dead and hurt, did alſo flie away, leauing behinde them their Fortes which weare, after ſtrenghtened by our Men, and ſo with Gods mercy are become Maſters of the Towne, hauing loſt in all about 50. or 60. Men.</p>
            <p>I haue beſett the Ieſuits Cloyſter (where I am lodged) with Trenches. The 20. February with conſent of the Counſell; wee did commaund Leftennant Steyncallenfells to make an Enterpriſe in the night vpon the Forte that ſtands vpon the Recyf towards the land, whoe hath quitted himſelfe therein, and ſtormed therevpon twoo houres long, but our lathers
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5162:7"/>being to ſhorte, was thought good to retire, to ſaue our men with the loſſe of 20. dead and 40. hurt of our Men, and 12. of theirs. Wherevpon the 23. February hauing thought fitting with conſent of the Counſell, to fall vpon the ſayd Towne with Approaches, wherevpon preſent order was given for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> preparation therevnto, which being done the 27. February<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wee begann the Worke vnder commaund of Leftennant Eltſz, who made the ſame night a Trench againſt the Caſtell, betweene this Towne and the Recyf, and the day following the Battery allmoſt finiſhed, and when Major Houcx went to relieue him, I went thether alſo and ſtayed there till the day following till the Battery was finiſhed: and three half Cannon planted therevpon, and hauing ſhott all that day and next day being the ſecond currant, hauing alſo ſhott the whole morning till about 9. a cloack, began to parle with mee, and ſett vp a white ſheete, ſending a Captaine vnto vs with whom I haue agreed, that they leauing the Forte, ſhall departe without ancient or burning Matches, leauing behinde them all Artillery, as alſo all Amunition and Proviſion, which wee thinck they haue caſte in the Sea and carryed away, becauſe wee found none therein. Further wee urged them to promiſe not to rayſe any Armes againſt the States in 6. Moneths. This being done, wee thought fitting to demaund the other Caſtel vpon the Recyf, which layes in the Sea. In the meane tyme the Generall, the Admirall and Vice-Admirall had notice thereof, who comming did approue thereof, and was putt in practiſe by ſending a Drumme, and they ſent out a Leften<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but leauing another in hoſtage, with whom by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from his Commandor wee agreed vpon conditions as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merlie, which beeing preſentlie ſubſcribed one both ſides, they marched out, and ſo in the afternoone wee were maſter of both Forts and Hauen, as alſo of the whole Recyf. The next day beeing the 3. March, wee gaue order to the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tennant Steyncallenfelts to make an aſſault vpon the Iland of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5162:7"/>Antonio Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> cituated ouer againſt the Village of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyf, which he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> put in practiſe, and beeing ſett ouer found noe bodie, there God bee praiſed, all beeing fled at the newes of the goeing ouer of the Towne and Caſtles, ſo that hee lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Troupe in the Cloiſter vpon the Iland, where with the Towne and ſtrong Holdes are all in our command none excepted, wee haueing wanted in this exploict the principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt Souldiours, which are yet behinde where my beſt men are, yea myn owne Companie, where is wanting all the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and aboute 1800. Men not manie more or les. I doubt not but my Lords the Directors of the Weſt-India Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie will ſecunde vs in this Victorie, to the ende they maye in time enioye the fruites hereof, and beeing as it is in effect a place (beeing ſecunded) invinceable of good tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, haueing good water and good fleſh, a place where moſt of the Trafique of all Braſill hath beene driuen, and beeing once ſetled in peace, by Gods grace ſhall bee driuen againe, and is abel to keepe in ſubiection all Braſill. With which I hope through the afright, which is in the whole Land, to make ſuch a progres in the Land, that your Highneſſes ſhall haue an euerlaſting name thereby, and ſo with this place keepe all the coaſt of Braſill in aw, and take awaye all there Traffique and the Navigation, which is the onelie meanes to withdraw the Traffique of theſe parts from our common Enimie the King of Spanie, and ſo bring the Inhabitants to a mutuale friendſhip and Aliance.</p>
            <p>The good God bleſſe and proſper your Highneſſes, and make you nurſers of his people, to the praiſe and glorie of his holie name, and confuſion of his and our Enimies.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Actum in the Ieſuits Cloiſter in the Towne of OLINDA de FERNABUCO <date>the 7. March 1630.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Was ſubſcribed your Highnes humble Seruant D. V. WEERDENBURGH.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="key_to_map">
            <pb facs="tcp:5162:8"/>
            <head>DECLARATION OF T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> the greate Fort vpon the Land-Recif, ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>orge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B</hi> the Fort vpon the Sea-Recif.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>C</hi> a niew began Fort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D</hi> Povo or Village by the Pack houſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>E</hi> Povo the Haven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>F</hi> the ſmale Fort vnder the Towne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G</hi> the Ieſuites Colledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H</hi> the greate Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> S. Berto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>K</hi> Carmo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>L</hi> S. Iuan.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M</hi> R. de la Vada.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="ger" type="view">
            <pb facs="tcp:5162:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:5162:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:5162:10"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>DA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>DE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> PHERNAMBVCO WELCHE DVRCH DEI HOLLENDER IM FEBRVARI 1630 EROBERT WORDEN.</head>
                  <figDesc>view of Farnabucco</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Ieſütten Kirch</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Groſse Kirch</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3 <hi>Das Gieſshaiſs.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4 <hi>Hafen do die Schiffverſüneken worden</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5. <hi>Kl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap> Schantz under der Stadt</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6 <hi>Groſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Schantz <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> Land Reciff</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>7 <hi>Schantz <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ffder See Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>ff</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>8. <hi>Packh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>tiſer ſo im Brank ſtehen</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>9 <hi>Brenn ende Barche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>10 <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ier iſt das volck <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ns Land geſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap> worden</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
